Some people say experience is
everything. It teaches you patience,
gives you time to sharpen your skills,
and make you overall a better human
being. Some even argue your peak [music]
aerobic fitness is reached at about 35
years old.
Well, if we believe these theories, I
should be at my prime and an absolute
weapon at mountain biking. I am 33,
relatively healthy, and I've been riding
since I'm 3, giving me about 30 years of
bike experience, meaning I've had 30
years to get good at mountain [music]
biking. Today, we're going to test this
theory because I will be racing against
Asa Vermette, which is possibly the
fastest 19-year-old on the planet.
You think that's a true statement? I
hope so. Asa is one of the most
decorated young guns of the sport with a
downhill junior world championship,
multiple [music]
Red Bull Hardline, and USA National
Championships under his belt. He picked
[music] up a Red Bull helmet before he
was 18 and is widely regarded as one of
the future legends of the sport.
Asa, so how do you approach a new track?
Like, let's say here in Medina, I don't
think you've really ridden here before,
you've only done the Hardline track. How
do you get into a new track and how do
you actually kind of like look at it and
get faster and faster as the day goes
on?
I feel like I've been pretty good just
through my riding career just like going
straight into a track I haven't really
ridden. I don't know why, but just like
going straight into something new, I've
been pretty quick. I mean, it takes just
a couple laps to get used to, and once
you know like the quick lines, I follow
Troy for a couple of times, yeah. Do you
think the the the trick to get faster is
to follow Troy into everything?
>> [laughter]
>> No, I mean, yeah, I do it your own way,
for sure. But, I mean, just however you
can get most comfortable on the track.
I've just I've just done it by like
riding by myself, really. If you had to
design a track today, something that
you'd be the fastest on than anyone
else, what would it be?
Probably something like turns and
there's like fast off-camber sections
[music]
and just like really quick rock gardens.
Just where people are usually scared to
go quick for some reason. That's where I
usually gain my time, so. Just in a
different braid.
Okay, so today we're going to race this
Australian National downhill track. But
I'm going to be cheating.
Before we get racing, Asa is going to
ride through a few of the top lines from
this national track, and I will be
following him in an attempt to steal his
lines for the race.
What a way to make a living. As Asa is
floating over rocks effortlessly and
blasting through dusty corners with no
grips, popping into the next section
with ease, carrying maximum speed, I
painfully try to fight gravity and keep
both wheels pointing down. This corner
is deceptively off camber, and the
entrance of the next section is a step,
which requires a lot of commitment to
pop into. Please excuse my underwear,
that's all I had left after a week of
filming hardline. In this section, Asa
was 3 seconds faster than me, which
makes him faster by a staggering 21%.
In this second section, Asa goes in and
gap into the rut. Doesn't look like much
on video, but it's actually quite the
pull.
Rolling the rock is obviously slower,
and I seem to be missing the ability to
carry speed and scrub like the big dogs.
My ego was a little bruised when I
realized he put 3 seconds into me on a
9-second run.
This section impresses me the most. Asa
is able to go full tilt into a G-out
compression, hold it, then keep going
with the fingers off the brake. I feel
like I would fold like a lawn chair if I
tried the Asa strategy, so I hit the
brakes harder, but it makes for bigger
compression due to the lack of speed.
Honestly, at this point in the edit, I
have lost the little hope I had to ever
call myself a good bike rider, so I'll
welcome the almost 30% slower speed on
this section.
Okay, so no comparison here, but I just
wanted to show you how much crap I carry
when I film episodes like this one.
All right, so how long do you think you
can give me and still beat me to the
bottom on that 2-minute track? We'll try
>> [laughter]
>> We'll try 40 seconds. Try 40 seconds.
Okay. I'll start the stopwatch right
when you leave. All right.
3 2 1 go.
Oh, he's going for it.
Okay, I've got 40 seconds. Honestly,
I got to start. I'm not too confident.
That might not be quite enough.
Cuz the kid is faster even though
I've been riding longer than he's been
riding,
which is
a little bit annoying, I'm not going to
lie.
Should be good.
See if we can catch him.
Also, I'm riding a rental bike, which
doesn't really help. Thank you. I know
it's giving me the direction here. Yeah,
in the pocket.
Zip up the pocket. All right, let's go.
No, I don't think he's
I'm guessing he's going to be
going by now, maybe.
Oh.
Not going up already.
Come on.
Oh.
AH.
STILL DON'T SEE ANY DUST.
IT. THERE'S a low line here.
Go. Oh.
Hit something.
Sorry, Medina Bike Park.
Hit a rental bike.
A few bomb holes here.
I don't know which line he's going to
take. It'd be interesting to see on the
camera.
Pretty better lines than me. Cuz he's
been training on that and
I'm trying to
giving it all I got with the
trying to do not to eat actually.
It's quite dry here, see?
Unlike Hardline going now.
I'm obviously using all the lines he
gives me,
but
can't really
Oh.
Here they are.
How big are they?
I think we're again.
I can't
I'm not sure if it's the same line as
you.
I still can't hear him.
I don't know. We're nearing
the bottom.
It's sunny.
It's starting to sun.
Good for me.
Oh, I don't want it to be close.
It's ripping off.
Oh, and we got him.
I think I can hear him already.
Woo!
Okay.
Yeah.
Woohoo!
Sweet.
>> [laughter]
>> That was sick.
That was fun.
Just at the end, that was good.
>> just at the end. I was like, uh, you
might not catch me. And then I just
started hearing you.
>> Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> That was close. That was sick. Yeah.
That was fun.
>> Yeah, that was good. Did you push a
little bit? A little bit, yeah. I kind
of messed up a couple things. It was my
first run. I was like, Yeah. But it was
good. Yeah, awesome. That was fun.